With product opportunity explorer, you can analyze market trends and individual product
performance in the Amazon store.
If you're beginning your product research journey, you
might want to take a look at broader category and subcategory trends to start.
This approach
can help you discover popular niches without a specific product idea in mind.
For example,
if you're in the office supply space and looking for your next product idea, you could select
the office products category to see a list of top performing niches within that space.
If you already have a specific product idea, you can take a more focused approach by searching
for a related product, feature, or category.
For example, let's say you sell home and
kitchen products and want to enter the spice rack space.
Searching for spice rack will show
you specific features that customers may be looking for, like magnetic spice rack, wooden
spice rack, or expandable spice rack.
Sort your results by clicking the arrows next
to each column header to see the highest or lowest values for any metric, giving you
a better understanding of the overall category performance.
The Filter Results feature helps
you narrow down your search to identify opportunities that align with your goals.
You can create
highly specific filter combinations paired with sorting to focus on the most relevant
niches to your strategy.
For example, if you want to find popular products within your
target price range, you can set a price range using the average price filter, then sort
by search volume in descending order.
If you sort again by number of top-clicked products,
you can spot potential niches where demand is growing, but competition isn't high.
Once
you've identified a niche you'd like to explore further, click the niche to see in-depth metrics.
Navigate to the Insights and Trends tab and toggle between Views to analyze your competition
and track your customer performance.
Select up to two metrics to plot in the chart and
view seasonal shopping patterns and spot growth opportunities.
For example, comparing search
volume with search conversion rate can reveal when customers are searching versus when they're
actually buying, which can be insightful for timing promotions or product launches.
Use the
average selling price metric to understand how price changes affect sales.
If you notice
that search conversion only increases when prices decline, consider building this into
your margin and pricing model before launching a new product in this space.
Use pricing history
to understand the best time to run deals and drop prices to ensure you're staying competitive.
A high average price, along with high search conversion rates, may suggest a less competitive
niche or a space where customers are willing to pay a premium price for a popular product.
If you create your own products, this could be an opportunity to develop a high quality
offering at a lower price.
If you source products, this could be an opportunity to add an offer
to top listings within the niche, especially if you notice a high out of stock rate.
Comparing
metrics like selling partner count, brand count, or product count alongside search volume can
help you assess how competitive a niche is.
High demand with a low selling partner or product
count can represent an opportunity to enter a less competitive niche, whereas a consistently low
brand count can suggest that a niche is dominated by particular brands already in the space.
High
product count with steady growth could suggest a niche is becoming more competitive.
Navigate to
the search terms tab and sort by total count and search conversion in descending order.
Look for
terms with crossover between high search volume and high search conversion rates.
This overlap
helps reveal customer demand and valued features.
Be sure to pay attention to click share.
A high
click share with low conversion may suggest an unmet customer demand.
Customer feedback is also
a great strategy to use for informing your product selections.
Watch the customer reviews
insights overview video in Seller Central to learn more.